Guide to the William Oberhardt Drawings and Papers 19xx-19xx PR 412
New-York Historical Society
William Oberhardt drawings and papers
19xx-19xx
New-York Historical Society
Oberhardt, William
PR 412
.01 Linear feet in..
tbd
Arrangement
tbd
Biographical / Historical
tbd
Conditions Governing Access
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lorianne Oberhardt Kelly, January 2020.
Scope and Contents
tbd
Charcoal drawings.; Portraits.; Advertising.; Commercial art.; Portrait drawing, American -- 20th century.
- Framed Drawings, 1903-1956, undated; 17.71 Linear feet in 32 flat file folders
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes about 105 drawings, mostly in charcoal, that were originally in frames at the time of acquisition by N-YHS. The container list identifies all drawings in the series. These are primarily portraits, primarily with a focus on heads. Most are identified. There are also some drawings other than portraits; these appear to be mostly related to advertising or commercial purposes.
  Information for the container list was taken from the drawings, labels, or backing. All frames were removed by N-YHS conservator Katarzyna Bator in January-February 2020. The backing was retained with the drawing if there was information written on it. In many cases, however, labels with identifying information (i.e., medium, subject name and (sometimes) identifying description, artist/Oberhardt's name)had been glued to the glass of the frame; these could not be removed and so were discarded with the glass. Information was recorded in the container list. Photos of the label were taken by the conservator and are on file with the lab's treatment report. Where identifying information was absent, the archivist provided some description in [brackets].
  Many of the backings include a prominent number. It is not known what this number represents, but it was included in the conatiner list note for the drawing.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged chronologically using the date noted on the drawing or label. Undated drawings are at the end, with titled objects first, followed by those not titled by the artist. Titles in [brackets] were given by the processing archivist.
  - "A Part of New York Where English is Not Spoken", 1903 (Folder FF-21)
    Drawing (color). Signed. From backing: "My first illustration made in 1903, published in Leslie's Weekly 1906"; "For Society of Illustrators Special Exhibition." Title is on backing; subject appears to be haggling with Jewish street vendors.
  - Hudson Maxim, 1909 (Folder FF-26)
    Charcoal. Signed. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "poet, inventor"
  - Joseph Pennell, 1918 (Folder FF-18)
    Charcoal. Signed. #1
  - Douglas Volk, 1919 (Folder FF-2)
    Charcoal. Signed. #13. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "artist"
  - H.T. Webster, 1919 (Folder FF-11)
    Charcoal. Signed. #27. From label: "cartoonist"
  - "Preliminary rough sketch for Fatima newspaper advertising", 1919-1920 (Folder FF-29)
    Charcoal. Signed. Image of men smoking and watching an event. Drawing stamped by Leggett & Myers Tobacco Co. Advertising Department, June 25, 1920, and initialed "OK.".
  - Charles C. Chambers, 1921 (Folder FF-19)
    Charcoal. Signed. #17. From backing: "illustrator"
  - Arthur I. Keller, 1921 (Folder FF-11)
    Charcoal. Signed. #20. From backing: "Illustrator"
  - Henry Cabot Lodge, 1921 October 25 (Folder FF-8)
    Lithograph. Signed, noted as Washington, DC. #64. Autographed by Lodge?
  - William H. Taft, 1921 October 27 (Folder FF-13)
    Lithograph. Signed, noted as Washington, DC. #101. Autographed by Taft? From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "Chief Justice"
  - John Alonzo Williams, 1921 (Folder FF-15)
    Charcoal. Signed. #23. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "illustrator"
  - "Play Time Stuff! Exhibition. The Society of Illustrators at The Art Center, 65 E. 56th St.", 1922 (Folder FF-18)
    Poster/Lithograph? Signed
  - Thomas A. Edison, 1922 August 12 (Folder FF-13)
    Lithograph. Signed. #20. Noted on drawing as "from life. On the 45th anniversary of the Ediphone." Autographed by Edison.
  - Joseph H. Chapin, 1923 March (Folder FF-23)
    Charcoal. Signed. #18. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1921-1922
  - Franklin Booth, 1925 (Folder FF-19)
    Charcoal. Signed. #11. Autographed by Booth?
  - D.W. Griffith, 1925 (Folder FF-5)
    Charcoal. Signed. #41. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "motion picture producer"
  - Thomas Meighan, 1925 (Folder FF-18)
    Charcoal. Signed. #70. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "actor"
  - "Pennell Memorial Exhibition", 1926 October 2-31 (Folder FF-24)
    Poster for event. Includes Oberhardt's 1918 drawing of Joseph Pennell (see above).
  - Walter Whitehead, [circa 1926?] (Folder FF-7)
    Charcoal. Signed. #115. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1925-1926
  - Peirce Johnson, 1927 (Folder FF-23)
    Charcoal. Initialed. #55. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "art director"
  - Lynn Bogue Hunt, 1930 (Folder FF-27)
    Charcoal. Signed. #15.
  - Walter Lippmann, 1931 (Folder FF-21)
    Charcoal. Signed. #62. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "newspaper editor, columnist"
  - Frank Weitenkamp (5 lithographs), 1932? (Folder FF-22)
    Lithographs (5). Signed. #113 (found on backing of print #8/50). Print #8/50 is dated 1932 and is the date used here; its backing is numbered #113. The other copies are undated, though the backing of #15/50 has a 1935 New York Water Color Club label on back. #15/50 has a notation on it: "1st prints made." The other three prints in the folder are numbered 26/50, 27/50, and 28/50.
  - Larry Hiller, 1933 (Folder FF-20)
    Charcoal. Signed. #4. "Larry Hiller" written on drawing; From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "Lejaren A. Hiller, photographer"
  - Canby, 1934 (Folder FF-21)
    Charcoal. Signed. #15. Written on drawing: "copyrighted by McCalls Magazine"
  - Dr. Hunt, 1934 (Folder FF-8)
    Charcoal. Signed. #51. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "Professor"
  - [Portrait of a Man], 1934 (Folder FF-17)
    Charcoal. Inscribed "To Ed, Obie"
  - [Portrait of Man with Round Eyeglasses], 1935 (Folder FF-6)
    Charcoal. Signed. Unidentified subject.
  - Harry Miller Lydenburg, 1936 (Folder FF-5)
    Charcoal. Signed. #67. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "Author and librarian"
  - "Study of H.S.N.", 1937 (Folder FF-25)
    Charcoal. Signed. #124.
  - Deane Uptegrove, 1937 (Folder FF-9)
    Charcoal. Signed. #105. From label on glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1936-1938.
  - Nathaniel Pousette-Dart, 1938 (Folder FF-20)
    Charcoal. Signed. #8. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1924-25, painter, author, editor". From backing: "for second annual exhibition of contemporary American drawing, the National Academy of Design. [struckthrough]"
  - C.D. Williams, 1938 (Folder FF-4)
    Charcoal. Signed. #18. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "Illustrator"
  - "Study", 1938 (Folder FF-29)
    Charcoal, color. Signed. #128. The title "Study" is taken from the label that was visible and adhered to the frame glass (discarded). A mat surrounding the drawing included the title "A Playtime Sketch," but this was not visible when the item was still in its frame. Also unseen, behind the drawing was a portrait of another man, drawn on the backing. On the exposed portion of the backing was recorded: "Study. Porter of the Architectural League, John Holden[?], native of the Barbados"
  - Louis Ruyl, 1939 (Folder FF-17)
    Charcoal. Signed. #14. Noted on drawing: "the speechless [illegible word?]" From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "artist"
  - Lester Jay Loh, 1940 (Folder FF-11)
    Charcoal. Signed. #65. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1940-1942. There is a different portrait drawn on reverse.
  - Walter B. Geoghegan, 1941 (Folder FF-6)
    Charcoal. Signed. #35. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1938-1940.
  - [Portrait of a Man], 1941 (Folder FF-7)
    Charcoal. Signed. Written in pencil on drawing: "for special news service, copyright, Associated Press, 1941"
  - "Teddy" [Portrait of an African-American Man], 1942 (Folder FF-27)
    Charcoal. Signed. #126.
  - Leroy P. Ward, 1942 (Folder FF-30)
    Charcoal. Signed. #25. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "architect"
  - C.D. Gibson, 1943 (Folder FF-4)
    Charcoal. Signed. #3 or #37? Autographed by Gibson? Noted as last portrait of Gibson.
  - Fred Grueger, 1943 (Folder FF-15)
    Charcoal. Signed. #2. From label: "illustrator"
  - Norman Price, 1944 (Folder FF-12)
    Charcoal (color). Signed. #29.
  - Clarence Birdseye, 1946 (Folder FF-13)
    Charcoal. Signed, as Glouchester. #8. From label on backing: "'The fabulous individual behind the household word.' Drawn from life for Readers Digest." From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "processed foods executive"
  - Paul de Kruif, 1946 (Folder FF-16)
    Charcoal. Signed. #23. From label on backing: "'Fighter for the right to live.' Drawn from life for Readers Digest." From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "writer"
  - Arthur Hawkins, Jr., 1946 (Folder FF-4)
    Charcoal. Signed. #7. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1945-46
  - Francis Cardinal Spellman, 1946 (Folder FF-15)
    Charcoal. Signed. #99. From backing: "Drawn from life for Readers Digest." Autographed by Spellman?
  - Harry Emerson Fosdick, D.D., 1947? (Folder FF-28)
    Charcoal. Signed.
  - "Sketch of Salisbury" [Sir Frank O. Salisbury], 1947 (Folder FF-30)
    Charcoal. Signed. #26. Autographed by Salisbury? From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "English portrait painter"
  - Hobart Nichols, 1948 (Folder FF-12)
    Charcoal. Signed. #78. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, National Academy of Design, 1939-49. "Hobart" written as "Hobert" on drawing and backing.
  - Bernard M. Baruch, 1949 (Folder FF-7)
    Charcoal. Signed. #5. From backing: "Drawn from life for Readers Digest" and "Art Director Member Exhibition, Riverside Museum"
  - Ira A. Hirschman, 1949 (Folder FF-28)
    Charcoal. Signed. #47. From label on backing: " Of WABF. Drawn from life for the Reader's Digest."
  - Sir Willmott Lewis, 1949 (Folder FF-7)
    Charcoal. Signed. #61. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "Washington correspondent for The London Times"
  - Harold Medina (Judge), 1949 (Folder FF-8)
    Charcoal. Signed. #69. From backing: "Judge Extraordinary" Drawn from life for Readers Digest.
  - Edward R. Murrow, 1949 (Folder FF-1)
    Charcoal. Signed. #75. Drawn from life for Readers Digest.
  - Dr. Cornelius Packard Rhoads, 1949 (Folder FF-28)
    Charcoal. Signed. #90. From label on backing: "Head of Sloan Kettering Institute for Cancer Research. Drawn from life for Reader's Digest."
  - Ralph J. Bunche, circa 1950 (Folder FF-27)
    Charcoal. Signed. #13. From label on backing: "Famed UN mediator who brought peace to the Holy Land. Nobel Prize winner. Drawn from life for the Reader's Digest."
  - Ed Reid, 1950 (Folder FF-9)
    Charcoal. Signed. #87. From backing: "Drawn from life for Readers Digest." From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "Reporter"
  - Dr. Harry M. Archer, 1951 (Folder FF-18)
    Charcoal. Signed. #2. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "Hon. Deputy Commissioner, N.Y.C. Fire Department"
  - Dr. Edgar Brower Burchell, 1951 (Folder FF-19)
    Charcoal. Signed. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "noted world authority on human eye and ear"
  - Christy, 1951 (Folder FF-25)
    Charcoal. Signed. #19.
  - John Foster Dulles, 1951 (Folder FF-9)
    Charcoal. Signed. #28. From backing: "Drawn from life for Readers Digest."
  - Study of W.H. de F., 1951 (Folder FF-14)
    Charcoal. Signed. #33. Oil(?) painting on back of a relgious cleric (cardinal?).
  - Herbert Hoover, 1951 (Folder FF-6)
    Charcoal. Signed. #50
  - Harry F. O'Brien, 1951 (Folder FF-10)
    Charcoal. Signed. #81 [or 80?]. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1950-1951.
  - Ezio Pinza, 1951 (Folder FF-5)
    Charcoal. Signed. #84. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "opera singer"
  - Roy W. Tillotson, 1951 (Folder FF-4)
    Charcoal, Signed. #22. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1951-1953.
  - Senator John J. Williams, of Delaware, 1951 (Folder FF-13)
    Charcoal. Signed. #118.
  - Captain Charles Blair, 1952 (Folder FF-18)
    Charcoal. Signed. #6. From label on backing: "Drawn from life for Readers Digest." From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "flyer"
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower, 1952 (Folder FF-4)
    Charcoal. Signed, noted as Denver, Colo. #30
  - Richard M. Nixon, 1952 (Folder FF-2)
    Charcoal. Signed, and noted "Denver, Colo." #79.
  - Richard Tucker, 1952 (Folder FF-12)
    Charcoal. Signed. #103. Another face drawn, in color, on reverse. From label on backing: "Met's phenomenal 'Italian' tenor. Drawn from life for Readers Digest." From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "opera singer"
  - John Jamison, 1953 (Folder FF-8)
    Charcoal. Signed. #53. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Art Directors Club of New York, 1953-1954
  - Ervine Metzl, 1953 (Folder FF-6)
    Charcoal. Signed. #28. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): President, Society of Illustrators.
  - Chief Magistrate Murdagh [or Murtagh], 1953 (Folder FF-12)
    Charcoal. Signed. #76.
  - Phil Rizzuto, 1953 (Folder FF-16)
    Charcoal. Signed. #91. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "baseball player"
  - Watson, 1953 (Folder FF-28)
    Charcoal. Signed. #110
  - Walter Lanier (Red) Barber, 1954 (Folder FF-1)
    Charcoal. Signed. #4. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "sports broadcaster"
  - C.C. Beall, 1954 (Folder FF-19)
    Charcoal. Signed. #6. From label adhered to frame glass: "artist"
  - Sidney Dickinson, 1954 (Folder FF-3)
    Charcoal. Signed. #24. Another face drawn on reverse.
  - Salvador Dali, 1955 (Folder FF-16)
    Charcoal. Signed. A portrait of a different man drawn on reverse.
  - [G. Keith?] Funston, 1955 (Folder FF-30)
    Charcoal. Signed. #33.
  - Krauss?, 1955 (Folder FF-11)
    Charcoal. Signed. #60. The label affixed to the glass of the original frame indicated that this was a portrait of artist Charles E. Chambers (label is in folder with drawing). However, Chambers died in 1941. Further, "Kraus" or "Krauss" is written at the bottom of the drawing and on the backing, so that seems to be the more likely subject.
  - Self Portrait, 1955 (Folder FF-3)
    Charcoal. Signed. #5. Another face drawn on reverse. From backing: "Exhibition of self portraits, March 1, 55" For Society of Illustrators [struckthrough].
  - Sylvester "Pat" Weaver, 1955 (Folder FF-28)
    Charcoal. Signed. #111. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "television executive"
  - Michael di Nunzio, 1956 (Folder FF-14)
    Charcoal. Initialed. #31. From label: "architect"
  - Glen L. Emmons, 1956 (Folder FF-23)
    Chsarcoal. Signed. #31.
  - James Montgomery Flagg, 1956 (Folder FF-5)
    Charcoal. Signed. #32
  - Profile of East Indian, undated (Folder FF-3)
    Charcoal. Signed. #132
  - Study of East Indian with Goatee, undated (Folder FF-10)
    Charcoal. Signed. #131.
  - "A demonstration sketch drawn at the Architectural League with Flagg as a model", undated (Folder FF-21)
    Charcoal. Initialed. Title written on drawing.
  - Ugo Mochi, undated (Folder FF-10)
    Charcoal. Signed. #10. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "artist"
  - H.S. Nichols, undated (Folder FF-14)
    Charcoal. Signed. #77. From backing: "for second annual exhibition of contemporary American drawing, the National Academy of Design." From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "editor"
  - Self Portrait, undated (Folder FF-2)
    Charcoal. Signed. #130
  - Emily Stevens, undated (Folder FF-33)
    Pastel. Signed. Title is on backing. Also on backing: "Group Exhibition of Pastels, Watercolors and Drawings, Becker Group"
  - Professor Ludwig von Herterich, undated (Folder FF-25)
    Charcoal and red chalk. Not signed. #39. From label adhered to frame glass (discarded): "German portrait painter"
  - "Illustration for Sanka[?] Coffee Advertisement", undated (Folder FF-17)
    Charcoal (color). Signed.
  - [Baseball players. Letter B on uniform], undated (Folder FF-1)
    Charcoal. Signed. From backing: "For illustrators. The New Rochelle Art Association Public Library, 11th annual"
  - [Horse drawn wagon with manufactured product], undated (Folder FF-24)
    Charcoal. Not signed. An Art Directors Club exhibition form on backing, though crossed out, indicates the following: Advertising Agency--Sterling McMielan Nash; Art Director--Ben Nash; Advertiser--Pyrene Manufacturing Co., of Newark, NJ.; and Product Advertsied--Pyrene.
  - [Brooklyn Bridge/Manhattan Bridge/Boats on East River], undated (Folder FF-27)
    Charcoal. Not signed.
  - [Woman gazing worriedly out her apartment window], undated (Folder FF-32)
    Charcoal. Signed. No title or description on backing.
  - [Portrait of a Man with Mustache], undated (Folder FF-9)
    Charcoal. Initialed.
  - [Portrait of a Scowling Man], undated (Folder FF-16)
  - [Profile of a Man], undated (Folder FF-17)
    Lithograph? Signed.
  - [Portrait of an Elderly Man], undated (Folder FF-22)
  - [Portrait of a Man], undated (Folder FF-26)
    Charcoal and chalk. Signed.
  - [Photoreproduction of portrait drawing], undated (Folder FF-3)
    Unidentified subject.
  - [Backing only; No drawing], undated (Folder FF-2)
    #80
- Drawings, Not Framed, 19xx-19xx; .01 Linear feet
  tbd
  - Portfolio Case of Drawings (4 folders), undated (Folder FF-31a-d)
    20 drawings and one poster found together in an oversize portfolio case.
    FF-31a holds 11 charcoal drawings of various scenes, all but one untitled, all but one signed: (descriptions from archivist's impressions) 1) what appears to be a young woman preparing to leave home while an older woman looks on; 2)three men in discussion in a produce store; 3) laborers looking at an "out of commission" machine (drawing stamped as property of The World Today); 4)stricken man lying on sidewalk (unsigned); 5) fearful man sitting in room; 6) salesman declining to accept a return of clothing from a customer; 7) "Money Back" appears to be a counterpoint to the previous drawing; 8) woman in discussion with two men in domestic setting; 9) men looking intently at discovered documents; 10) man painting shelves in a produce store (drawing stamped as property of The world Today); 11) man carrying chairs up stairs (bottom torn off).
    FF-31b holds 7 objects: 1) small charcoal portrait of a conductor (unsigned); 2) charcoal portrait of Michele A. Schmidt of Albuquerque, U.S. Army, signed, drawn in New York, December 1942; 3) two businessmen looking in amazement at an assertive woman dressed fashionably; 4)woman pouring coffee for a man as boy looks on; 5) four men drinking cocktails, color, unsigned; 6) color drawing for poster for Kuppenheimer Good Clothes; 7) poster saluting the Great White Fleet/Merchant Marine from United Fruit Company (World War II period).
    FF-31c holds 3 boards with 6 portraits of men and women painted on them, color, unsigned.
    FF-31d holds the original portfolio case.